<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-03T22:13:15+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ishank’s Webpage</title><subtitle>Personal homepage: Ishank Juneja</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Advances in Radioisotope and Isotope Technologies by the Indian Atomic Energy Program</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/radioIsotopes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Advances in Radioisotope and Isotope Technologies by the Indian Atomic Energy Program" /><published>2020-08-01T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-08-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/radioisotopes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/radioIsotopes">&lt;p&gt;The Central Government realized early on in India’s independence that moving forward, Nuclear Technology would be crucial to pulling the nation out of the many challenges it faced. The problems included a paucity of domestic &lt;strong&gt;coal and fossil fuel&lt;/strong&gt; and an impoverished populace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To fulfill these needs the Department of Atomic energy (henceforth referred to as the &lt;strong&gt;DAE&lt;/strong&gt;) was instituted in 1954. Given the importance of the DAE, ever since its inception, the Department has been under the direct charge of the Prime Minister’s Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nuclear Power is the contribution of the DAE that has been at the center of the public eye. However, DAE is a multifaceted organisation with contributions across numerous areas of Nuclear Science, Industry and Technical Education. Additionally, over the decades the organisation has placed a high emphasis on basic research. The DAE now includes five research centers and the world renowned &lt;strong&gt;TIFR institute&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two factors that have greatly &lt;strong&gt;improved&lt;/strong&gt; the quality of life in India are electrical power and a secure food supply. Firstly, it would be appropriate to highlight the achievements of the DAE in Nuclear Power. India has a total of seven nuclear power plants, collectively they have an installed capacity of nearly 7000 MW. This installation alone is sufficient to power nearly &lt;strong&gt;50,000 Indian households&lt;/strong&gt;. Further the Nuclear Power Corporation has planned several new plants including the &lt;strong&gt;Jaitapur&lt;/strong&gt; Nuclear Power Plant. When completed, the Jaitapur Plant will have a generation capacity of 9900 MW. This would make it the &lt;strong&gt;largest capacity&lt;/strong&gt; Nuclear power plant in the world. A proud achievement for the research arms of the DAE is the fact that India is the &lt;strong&gt;world leader in Thorium&lt;/strong&gt; thermal breeder reactor technology. Amongst the many technologies developed for the utilisation of Thorium as a nuclear fuel, the Advanced Heavy Water Reactor is operational.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the area of &lt;strong&gt;agriculture&lt;/strong&gt;, scientists working at &lt;strong&gt;BARC&lt;/strong&gt; have created &lt;strong&gt;high yield&lt;/strong&gt; and stress resistant varieties using radiation induced mutations. These crop varieties have contributed to higher revenues for farmers and have ensured a stable food supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isotopes are atoms of the same element having different atomic mass. Some isotopes have unstable nuclei, this makes them &lt;strong&gt;radioactive&lt;/strong&gt; and they are termed as &lt;strong&gt;Radioisotopes&lt;/strong&gt;. These unstable isotopes attain stability by radiating alpha particles, beta particles or gamma rays. Isotopes are extremely useful since different isotopes of the same element share identical chemical properties. This allows scientists to chemically react isotopes and radioisotopes in predictable ways and use them to create desired compounds and reagents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since radioisotopes and other special isotopes are immensely important, it is crucial that they be &lt;strong&gt;produced domestically&lt;/strong&gt; in a cost effective manner.The creation of isotopes that do not occur naturally involves bombarding the nuclei of a raw target material with subatomic particles like neutrons. This process can take place either in a particle accelerator or a Nuclear reactor. Out of these two methods, production in particle accelerators is not commercially viable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radioisotope production in commercial reactors uses neutron capture by the target material. The source of these neutrons are thermal neutrons generated from a &lt;strong&gt;chain reaction&lt;/strong&gt;. The chain reaction is important since it allows a substantial amount of isotope to accumulate. Since the procedure for creating radioisotopes is intricate and sensitive, setting up the required infrastructure has been a challenging task for the government. Today India is capable of synthesising a plethora of important radioisotopes in a cost effective manner. This has been made possible by the efforts taken by researchers from DAE and the early leadership of &lt;strong&gt;Dr. Homi Bhabha&lt;/strong&gt; - The architect of India’s Nuclear program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isotopes hold an important position in the world of medicine and Healthcare. Radioisotopes are used in both diagnostic and therapeutic applications. These special isotopes are incorporated in &lt;strong&gt;radiopharmaceuticals&lt;/strong&gt; and diagnostic &lt;strong&gt;markers&lt;/strong&gt;. These energy emitting radioactive isotopes can be used to provide an internal image, thereby acting like a &lt;strong&gt;diagnostic agent&lt;/strong&gt;. On the other hand radiopharmaceuticals can also be directly healing towards tissue, giving them a therapeutic application. These drugs are administered to lakhs of people annually for various needs like cardiac function assessment and cancer treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the field of nuclear medicine has been around for a long time, there have been numerous breakthroughs made in recent years. This is especially true for prostate, neuroendocrine and liver cancer &lt;strong&gt;diagnosis and treatment&lt;/strong&gt;. On the diagnosis side, BARC has developed &lt;strong&gt;radio-immunoassay&lt;/strong&gt; technology. An immunoassay is a device that is used to detect and quantify the presence of biomarker proteins such as excessive &lt;strong&gt;PSA&lt;/strong&gt; (Prostate specific antigen). When immunoassay technology is combined with radioisotopes, a more accurate quantification can be achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another tool required in the diagnosis of cancer is internal body imaging. This technique is required to search for tumours within various organs of the body. BARC and other organisations working under the umbrella of the DAE have developed the pharmaceutical &lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;99m&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tc-Sulphur&lt;/strong&gt; Colloid for imaging the liver. Radiopharmaceuticals such as the mentioned colloid provide doctors with a clearer picture of the internals of the liver thereby making the diagnosis of liver cancer more reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indian scientists have also made strides in cancer therapy to cure and prevent the spread of these cancers. Dr. Rubel Chakravarty’s team at BARC has recently, in &lt;strong&gt;2018&lt;/strong&gt;, published their work on targeted &lt;strong&gt;alpha therapy&lt;/strong&gt; in prostate cancer using radioisotope labelled biomarkers. This new technique is promising and would play a pivotal role in the treatment of prostate cancer in the years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With improved lifestyles, the average life expectancy has gone up. Cancer is an ailment that is more likely to occur during &lt;strong&gt;old age&lt;/strong&gt;. Since Indians are living longer lives than before, the number of &lt;strong&gt;cancer cases&lt;/strong&gt; have gone up tremendously. The problem is serious to the extent that approximately &lt;strong&gt;8 Lakh new cases&lt;/strong&gt; are diagnosed each year and cancer has become the &lt;strong&gt;4th highest&lt;/strong&gt; cause of adult mortality in India. Due to contributions of nuclear science, an effective cancer treatment is available in the form of &lt;strong&gt;radiation therapy (Radiotherapy)&lt;/strong&gt;. Radiotherapy plays an important role in curing early stage cancer. The main methodologies for performing radiotherapy are &lt;strong&gt;Teletherapy and Brachytherapy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teletherapy involves delivering radiation from an emitter that is placed at a distance from the patient’s body. In the early days of teletherapy, the procedure was quite harmful to healthy skin, bone and organ tissue. Over the decades the technology has improved by leaps and bounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent machine for teletherapy developed by BARC is the &lt;strong&gt;Bhabhatron&lt;/strong&gt;. The current iteration of the device is &lt;strong&gt;Bhabhatron-II&lt;/strong&gt;. The machine has numerous advanced features like asymmetric collimation, motorized wedge filter and collimator auto setup. The machine uses a special high activity isotope - &lt;strong&gt;Cobalt-60&lt;/strong&gt; as its radiation source. Bhabhatrons are now commonplace in cancer hospitals around India. They are the preferred choice over imported teletherapy machines since the Bhabhatron is &lt;strong&gt;cheaper and superior&lt;/strong&gt; in features. The fact that other countries import Bhabhatron devices are a testament to their quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other popular variant of radiotherapy is brachytherapy. Unlike teletherapy which is radiation from a distance, brachytherapy involves delivering radiation from a source placed in close  &lt;strong&gt;proximity&lt;/strong&gt; of the target area. For a long time after the discovery of &lt;strong&gt;Radium&lt;/strong&gt;, the popular way of performing brachytherapy was to use a paste of Radium and Barium Chloride and apply it over the skin. Nowadays the isotopes popular in brachytherapy are &lt;strong&gt;Iodine-125 and Caesium-137&lt;/strong&gt;. Iodine-125 emits a moderate amount of radiation, this ensures that only the cells of the body which uptake the radioactive Iodine atom are affected. Brachytherapy is popular in the treatment of prostate cancer and &lt;strong&gt;uveal melanomas&lt;/strong&gt; (tumours in the eye). Caesium-137 has a half life shorter than I-125. This means that it decays faster and has a slightly larger radiation level which makes it suitable for treatment of cancer in &lt;strong&gt;larger organs&lt;/strong&gt; like the cervix. In this case the procedure is referred to as &lt;strong&gt;intracavitary&lt;/strong&gt; brachytherapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important medical technology that makes use of radioisotopes is &lt;strong&gt;blood irradiation&lt;/strong&gt;. Blood irradiation is needed to make sure that blood transfused to an ailing patient is free from infections and bacteria. The sterilization happens using radioisotopes such as &lt;strong&gt;Cobalt-60&lt;/strong&gt; and Cesium-137. The &lt;strong&gt;Board of Radiation and Isotope Technology&lt;/strong&gt; (BRIT) has developed an indegenous blood irradiator called **BI 2000. **The device is available for purchase by hospitals and has proven to be popular given its quality and cost effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is evident from the above discussion the facilitation of all medical device technology requires the production of special isotopes with a &lt;strong&gt;high purity&lt;/strong&gt;. In India, this has been made possible by the setup of specialised &lt;strong&gt;medical cyclotrons&lt;/strong&gt;. Two of India’s primary medical cyclotron facilities are the Variable Energy Cyclotron Centre (&lt;strong&gt;VECC&lt;/strong&gt;) in Kolkata and the medical cyclotron facility (&lt;strong&gt;MCF&lt;/strong&gt;) installed at Tata Memorial Hospital, Mumbai.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is a developing nation and the economy requires a constant impetus from industry to meet the needs and aspirations of the nation’s growing population. In view of this, it would be relevant to emphasize the contribution of isotope technology to &lt;strong&gt;industrial applications&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important industrial application is that of &lt;strong&gt;non destructive testing&lt;/strong&gt;. Radiography (radiation mapping) can be used to inspect the strength of materials without physical contact. It is interesting to understand how this procedure works. When radiation passes through an object it undergoes &lt;strong&gt;absorption and scattering&lt;/strong&gt;. The extent of absorption and resulting scattering patterns depend on the material and &lt;strong&gt;internal structure&lt;/strong&gt; of the object. Knowledge from such testing allows us to estimate wear and tear. This is especially important for materials used in &lt;strong&gt;high stress&lt;/strong&gt; applications like boilers, nuclear reactors, aircraft and oil rigs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important industrial application of isotopes are &lt;strong&gt;radiotracers&lt;/strong&gt;. A tracer is a substance that helps detect and quantify a target. Conventional tracers utilise &lt;strong&gt;dyes and chemicals&lt;/strong&gt;, however radioisotope markers provide &lt;strong&gt;many advantages&lt;/strong&gt; over them. An important advantage of radioisotopes over conventional chemical tracers is that they can be detected in very low quantities making them a more sensitive tracer. Some examples of the use of radiotracers are &lt;strong&gt;Carbon-14&lt;/strong&gt; labelled oils and **Tritium **labelled water in crude oil fields. Tracking the movement of these isotopes allows for better management of the petroleum extraction process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clean water is an essential resource and &lt;strong&gt;managing fresh-water&lt;/strong&gt; resources is another area where radioisotopes are useful. Factories produce a lot of &lt;strong&gt;effluents&lt;/strong&gt; which harm water quality and aquatic ecosystems. Before an industry is granted clearance for discharging effluents into a water body, experimental studies must be conducted to understand their impact on the body.     A brilliant example of this is the use of radiotracers to study the &lt;strong&gt;dilution and dispersion&lt;/strong&gt; pattern of domestic sewage as it enters the sea at Colaba and Malad. This study, conducted in 1992, helped shape policy about &lt;strong&gt;sewage treatment&lt;/strong&gt; prior to discharge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Utilising radioisotopes for enhancing agricultural output is of critical significance to the Indian economy. The primary applications of nuclear science in agriculture are &lt;strong&gt;enhanced crop varieties&lt;/strong&gt; through induced mutations and &lt;strong&gt;radiation processing&lt;/strong&gt; of food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mutations can be introduced &lt;strong&gt;artificially&lt;/strong&gt; by irradiation with ionizing gamma radiation. New varieties of &lt;strong&gt;groundnuts and legumes&lt;/strong&gt; are success stories of this enhancement programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasing the shelf life of agricultural produce is mandatory if the aim is to ensure a stable food supply and a reliable incomes for farmers. The tropical climate in India is an ideal breeding environment for insects, mould and microbes, this leads to a low &lt;strong&gt;shelf-life&lt;/strong&gt; for produce. Processing food with radiation increases its shelf-life. Further it provides an alternative to &lt;strong&gt;chemical fumigants&lt;/strong&gt; which are harmful for both the environment and humans that come in contact with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researching the achievements and history of the DAE has given me immense pride as an Indian citizen. The growth that India’s civil nuclear program has seen since independence is unparalleled across the world. The nation now has a vast network of infrastructure for production and research related to nuclear science. The vision of exemplary leaders like Dr. Bhabha had inspired a generation to reach where we are today and continues to inspire the next generation of researchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dae.gov.in/node/91&quot;&gt;Saga of Atomic Energy in India Commerative Volume-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dae.gov.in/node/118&quot;&gt;DAE reports and documentation on Atomic Energy Programs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.barc.gov.in/clip/bhabhatron.html&quot;&gt;BARC report on the Bhabhatron&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This essay was written as an entry for the 31st DAE (Dept. of Atomic Energy) All India Online Essay Contest on Nuclear Science &amp;amp; Technology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Central Government realized early on in India’s independence that moving forward, Nuclear Technology would be crucial to pulling the nation out of the many challenges it faced. The problems included a paucity of domestic coal and fossil fuel and an impoverished populace.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Digital Video Stabilization</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/videoStab" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digital Video Stabilization" /><published>2020-07-30T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-30T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/video</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/videoStab">&lt;p&gt;Mechanical stabilization is well known. There external equipment such as camera gimblas and other apparatus are used to filter out vibrations. However, the capability of such equipment is limited to prventing high frequency vibrations from entering camera footage.
To tackle low frequency vibrations arising from actions such as walking and or running while recording video footage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stages of digital Video stabilization-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Motions estimation: Transformation parameters between 2 consecutive frames are derived&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Motion smoothing: Filtering out unwanted motion - Part where we generate the filter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Image composition: Reconstruction of a stabilized video&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;video-stabilisation-using-feature-points&quot;&gt;Video Stabilisation using feature points&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Track a few feature points between consecutive frames&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tracked features allow us to estimate the motion between subsequrnt frames and subsequently correct for it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;paramteric-linear-motion-models&quot;&gt;Paramteric Linear Motion Models&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What should be the transform that facillitates the application of a motion model
Heirarchy of transforms from computer vision&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Homography&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Affine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Euclidean (length preserving)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Translation
For the purpose of video stabilization, a&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;l1-optimal-camera-paths-paper-implementation-details&quot;&gt;L1 optimal camera paths paper implementation details&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paper focusses exclusively on 2D motion models (which is fair I guess)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can compare sparse optical flow (good when sharp features are avaiable) and dense optical flow (good when smooth features are present), both are implemented in openCV &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.opencv.org/3.3.1/d7/d8b/tutorial_py_lucas_kanade.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the paper they have gone for the sparse optical flow method&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Mechanical stabilization is well known. There external equipment such as camera gimblas and other apparatus are used to filter out vibrations. However, the capability of such equipment is limited to prventing high frequency vibrations from entering camera footage. To tackle low frequency vibrations arising from actions such as walking and or running while recording video footage.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Clock Controller Design</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/nixieClockController" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Clock Controller Design" /><published>2020-07-24T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-24T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/nixie-clock-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/nixieClockController">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/controller_annotated.png&quot; alt=&quot;Controller Board Annotated Image&quot; height=&quot;350&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is Part 3 in a three part series on our design of a USB powered Nixie Tube Clock display. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/nixieClock&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; discusses the characterization of Nixie tubes. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/nixieClockPower&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt; discusses the design of the power supply that steps up 5V to 170V.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;controller-board-overview&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Controller Board Overview&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The controller board a.k.a the USB bridge circuit is responsible for taking in timing information via USB from the host computer and displaying it, through the means of electrically isolated control signals, onto the front end display module consisting of 6 Nixie Tubes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;align: left; text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/block_diagram.png&quot; height=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; Complete Block Diagram &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The flow of information and power is illustrated in the above block diagram. From the above block diagram, Nixie Tube Driver Module, Micro-controller and the Nixie Tubes are all part of the controller board. The details of these and some of their sub-components are illustrated next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;usb-controller-circuit&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;USB Controller Circuit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting component of the controller board is the USB micro-controller circuit. The host computer, which could be a single board computer for portability and compactness, is connected to the USB controller. After which the host side USB interface program first uploads the firmware onto the controller and then streams time information data to it. The firmware and host side program software was written with help from our advisor Prof. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ee.iitb.ac.in/~mukul/&quot;&gt;Mukul Chandorkar&lt;/a&gt; and is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ishank-juneja/TUSB3210-Controller&quot;&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two alternatives were considered for the USB controller circuit - the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ti.com/lit/ds/slls466g/slls466g.pdf?ts=1595438237932&amp;amp;ref_url=https%253A%252F%252Fwww.google.com%252F&quot;&gt;TUSB3210&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ftdichip.com/Support/Documents/DataSheets/ICs/DS_FT232R.pdf&quot;&gt;FT232R&lt;/a&gt; chip. Our initial preference leaned towards the the FT232 from the desire for greater simplicity. Some problems with timing that could not be precisely controlled lead to us picking the TUSB3210 RAM based micro-controller. The details of these problems could be quite relevant to some other work and are available in our &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/docs/DD08_Design_Lab_report.pdf&quot;&gt;project report&lt;/a&gt;. To use the TUSB3210 controller in the USB connection circuit, some additional circuitry like its own power supply and some resetting circuitry were also needed. The details of these elements are also present in our project report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting question that needed to be answered was - What part of the processing should occur on the embedded controller and what parts should be done by the host computer? We pushed all the time keeping and computation onto the host computer leaving the USB controller with only the burden of two things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(1) Translating the digits of time being streamed from the host to control signals that the display front end can understand and&lt;br /&gt; 
(2) Using the control signals to multiplex between the various tubes in such a way that only a single tube is turned on at a time. This is required since the power available from the USB power source is, in principle, enough to light up only a single tube as discussed in &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/nixieClock&quot;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;optocoupler-isolation-and-control-signals&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optocoupler isolation and Control Signals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GPIO pins on the microcontroller are responsible for the control signals that display the time on the Nixie Tubes. The design is configured in a manner that there are 10 control signals. The breakdown being - 6 signals for selection among the 6 tubes and 4 signals for digit selection among the digits 0-9 using a Binary Coded Decimal (BCD) code. In a more optimized design, the 6 tube selection signals could be replaced by 3 control signals and a decoder chip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While designing the USB controller circuit described in the previous section, we thought that the 10mA or so of current required to turn the internal LEDs of the optocouplers on would be available from the GPIO pins of the controller itself. This assumption was based on a faulty reading of the somewhat unclear data sheet of the TUSB3210 controller. Since sufficient current could not be sourced from the controller directly, there had to be a current amplification stage sitting between the optocoupler input port (which is essentially an LED) and the signals being received from the GPIO pins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align: left; text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/GPIO_ckt.jpg&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; Configuration for a single signal &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The current amplifier stage is essentially BJTs configured as switches which turn on when there is a small current going into the base of the transistors. The base current requirement is small enough that the GPIO pins from the TUSB controller can provide it. The complete arrangement for a single control signal is described in the above image. When the MCU GPIO signal is high, the BC547 transistor turns on which in turn switches on the IR LED at the input port of the optocoupler. Once the input LED is on, it excites the photo-sensitive base of the output photo-transistor which turns the transistor on. In the configuration available to us only the collector terminal of the output transistor is available to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As shown in the above circuit diagram, this would lead to the output signal being 5V high when the photo-transistor if off, and low when the photo-transistor is on. This is a problem since the photo-transistor needs to be turned on really hard for the output taken at the collector terminal of the transistor to be low enough for the subsequent electronic stage (which is the display front end) to recognize it as off. This forced us to pick a very low resistance value for the optocoupler input LED. As seen in the above diagram this value is 30 Ω. With such a low series resistance, the current pushed through the LED is high at about 30mA. This also reduces the life of the input LED significantly. We found ourselves replacing the optocoupler ICs quite often during testing. The only possible solutions to this problem seem to be either to look for an optocoupler IC that uses a very sensitive photo-transistor or to somehow change the sensitivity of the electronics following the output of the optocoupler to have a very high threshold for the on state, close to the high logic level of 5V DC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-display-front-end&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Display Front End&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;align: left; text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nixie_ckt.jpg&quot; height=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; Digit and Tube control &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The display front end is where the previously mentioned 10 control signals get utilized. Four of these signals, marked A-D in the above diagram, are responsible for digit selection via the 74141 open collector decoder IC and the other six are for making a single Nixie tube light up at a time, that is to implement time multiplexing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;multiplexing-and-tube-control&quot;&gt;Multiplexing and Tube control&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six control signals are dedicated to selecting which tube turns on at any given time. The sequential turning off and on of tubes is implemented using a pair of BJT transistors as shown in the lower half of the above image. The arrangement of the pair of transistors is a variant of the darlington pair arrangement called the Sziklai Darlington Transistor Configuration and is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.electronics-tutorials.ws/transistor/darlington-transistor.html&quot;&gt;described here&lt;/a&gt;. The configuration uses a high voltage NPN (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.onsemi.com/pub/Collateral/MPSA42-D.PDF&quot;&gt;MPSA42&lt;/a&gt;) and a high voltage PNP (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.onsemi.com/pub/Collateral/MPSA92-D.PDF&quot;&gt;MPSA92&lt;/a&gt;) transistor to effectively achieve stronger current amplification than a single BJT switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this configuration, the Nixie tube would turn on when its corresponding NPN transistor (MPSA42 BJT) is on. To the outside circuit, the BJT pair simply appears as a highly sensitive NPN transistor since when the outer NPN transistor turns on, there is a sufficient base current coming out of the base current of the inner MPSA92 PNP transistor. This allows current to flow through the Nixie tube which turns it on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the high sensitivity of the transistor pair, the threshold for the low logic level comes out to be quite low. As described in the previous section, this leads to requirements on the optocoupler. The optocoupler input LEDs have to be turned on quite strongly so that the its corresponding output phototransistor turns on strongly and gives a ‘low enough’ (about 0.3V in this case) logic low voltage level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the broader design of the optocoupler transmitting the control signal to the high voltage side, we identify a somewhat serious problem with the described design. The problem being that if we consider the default state of the optocoupler input LED to be off, then this means that the default state of the output phototransistor for each signal is off and its output is therefore high, this in turn means that the default state of any Nixie tube is on. Since we wish to turn on a single Nixie tube at a time (the goal of multiplexing), this means that 5 out of 6 optocoupler input LEDs need to be turned on strongly for 5 unselected tubes to be off at all times. Signal inversion at the high voltage end or some other changes in the design can solve this problem and can reduce wear on the optocoupler LEDs in addition to decreasing power usage significantly on the low voltage USB side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;digit-selection-using-the-74141-ic&quot;&gt;Digit Selection using the 74141 IC&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each Nixie Tube has a total of twelve pins, one Anode and eleven cathodes corresponding to the digits 0-9 and a decimal point. Barring the decimal point, there needs to be a mechanism to choose between the 10 digits at any given instant. An off the shelf solution is available for the same in the form of the &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/docs/sn74141.pdf&quot;&gt;SN74141 TTL IC&lt;/a&gt;. The differences between the 74141 and a regular BCD decoder such as the 7442 are the presence of open collector outputs with Zener Diode Clamping and the use of high voltage rating transistors at the outputs in case of the 74141 which are absent in the 7442. This is crucial for the Nixie tube application since a large voltage could appear on the cathodes corresponding to digits that aren’t turned on for a tube that is glowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the 74141 IC the low level input voltage is allowed to be up to 0.8V. This requirement is not as strenuous as the one for turning off a Nixie tube but the problem of turning on the input LED of an optocoupler strongly to achieve a low logic level at the phototransistor output still holds true but the issue with the default value of a phototransistor being on is not a problem since the required input signals onto the pins A-D are a mix of high and low levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SN74141 IC is not the ideal way to implement digit selection for the Nixie tubes since the chip has now been discontinued. Further we found the 74141 to be quite unreliable with numerous failures during the testing process. A reproducible and more reliable approach would be to use high voltage shift registers (a.k.a serial to parallel convertors). In this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7uogKucrPks&quot;&gt;design exercise&lt;/a&gt; that creates a Nixie tube display, Dave from the EEVBlog recommends using the HV5622 or other similar ICs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-complete-board-view&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Complete Board View&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final board design is quite elegant and symmetrical in our opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;align: left; text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/controller_brd.png&quot; height=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; Complete board view of the controller board &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This project was completed in partial fulfilment of the requirements for EE 344: Electronic Design Lab at IITB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A more detailed description of the project along with schematics can be found in our &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/docs/DD08_Design_Lab_report.pdf&quot;&gt;project report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A demonstration of our project can be &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/MN-FbMPmbiw&quot;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Power Supply Design</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/nixieClockPower" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Power Supply Design" /><published>2020-07-16T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-16T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/nixie-clock-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/nixieClockPower">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ps_annotated.png&quot; alt=&quot;Power Supply&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is Part 2 in a three part series on our design of a USB powered Nixie Tube Clock display. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/nixieClock&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; discusses the characterization of Nixie tubes. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/nixieClockController&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt; describes the design of a circuit which controls the display using isolated control signals.&lt;br /&gt;
This work on the design of the power supply was spearheaded by Anantha Hegde and Yojit Srivastava.
***&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This page is about the design of the power supply module from our USB powered Nixie Tube clock display project. Since the USB source voltage is 5V DC and the operating voltage of the Nixie Tube display units is close to 180V DC, we needed to design a power supply capable of achieving this voltage step up. DC-DC power conversion and a large difference between input and output voltage difference mandated a switched mode (SMPS) isolated power supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the high output voltage level required, the convertor still operates in the low power regime (about 2.5 W as explained in &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/nixieClock&quot;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt;). This made the Flyback convertor topology ideal for our purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;related-existing-solutions---survey&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related Existing Solutions - Survey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we describe the solution we ended up implementing to reach the described end goal, let us look at some of the other solutions we considered prior to it. On scouring the web we found a few solutions that matched our requirement closely. Most of these solutions had an input operating voltage of 9V-12V. Perhaps this restriction of a slightly higher than available input voltage has something to do with most batteries (Lead Acid for example) having a terminal voltage in that range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;single-ic-based-solutions&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Single IC Based solutions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;tny-278&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TNY-278&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our first attempt at a Power Supply was with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.power.com/sites/default/files/product-docs/tny274-280.pdf&quot;&gt;TNY-278&lt;/a&gt; IC by Power Integrations. This was our starting point since this chip was available in our project advisors lab. The TNY-278 is a switching IC which has a typical application of a step down convertor in a flyback like type topology (can be seen in linked &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.power.com/sites/default/files/product-docs/tny274-280.pdf&quot;&gt;data sheet&lt;/a&gt;). Our intention was to reverse the input and output ports of its typical application circuit to use the chip in a step up convertor. However, we soon realized that the usage of such a topology with a 5V input voltage would not be possible since the internal circuitry of the TNY-278 makes any voltage below 5.85V unusable. However, we never showed that the operation of the TNY-278 IC could be mirrored in the first place. We simply rejected the idea since it would certainly not work with a 5V input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;lm3488&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LM3488&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quite close to the start of our work we came across &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/esynr3z/nixie-ps&quot;&gt;this well documented project&lt;/a&gt;. The linked project describes the design of a Flyback convertor that steps up 5-12V to 180V. On the surface of it, this seemed like the end to our search. In fact we even went ahead and got a circuit board printed for this circuit. The schematic and the board view are pictured below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;align: left; text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/LM3488.png&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; A non isolated Boost convertor &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The circuit is essentially a Flyback topology built around the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ti.com/lit/ds/snvs089o/snvs089o.pdf?ts=1594663885165&amp;amp;ref_url=https%253A%252F%252Fwww.google.com%252F&quot;&gt;LM 3488&lt;/a&gt; IC. The LM 3488 is the complete package as far as a switched power supply (SMPS) is concerned since it has voltage feedback from the output (FB pin), MOSFET gate drive (DR) and the switching frequency set (FA/SYNC/SD) all built into a single package. However, the design in the linked project destroyed the isolation obtained from the transformer of the Flyback convertor by sending in a direct voltage feedback from the HV side to the LV side without optocoupler isolation in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this was a critical design flaw for our application (the need for isolation is described in the next section) we decided to look for our own solutions starting from scratch. So, next began the phase of designing switched mode convertors from scratch using discrete components rather than packaged IC solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;discrete-components-based-solutions&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discrete Components Based Solutions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;initial-design-process---boost-convertor&quot;&gt;Initial Design Process - Boost Convertor&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;align: left; text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/boost.svg&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; A non isolated Boost convertor &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We started off the design process by putting together a Boost convertor. The question of whether a MOS or a BJT should be used as the electronic switch in our design was asked. Compared to a MOSFET, a BJT has a slower transient response and higher losses due to a continuous base current and a higher voltage drop across the Collector - Emitter junction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our choice of MOSFET was the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.infineon.com/dgdl/irfz44npbf.pdf?fileId=5546d462533600a40153563b3a9f220d&quot;&gt;IRFZ44N&lt;/a&gt;. This MOSFET fell well within the voltage and current ranges in which we would eventually want to operate our Flyback convertor switch. We tried switching this MOSFET using a switching frequency of 100KHz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;align: left; text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/not_switch.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;  Input Signal (Above) from an AFG and Faulty MOSFET Drain Signal (Below)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Initially when this was tried with the switching signal, a square wave of 100KHz, was provided directly to the date drive (pin) of the MOSFET. Soon we realized that the analog function generator (AFG), is unable to provide sufficient current for the MOSFET to be able to switch fast enough. This leads to the faulty on-off waveform in blue in the above figure. This calls for the need of a separate gate-drive stage which takes in a switching signal without imposing a load on it and echoes the same signal to a high current capacity gate-drive line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our initial design used the &lt;a href=&quot;http://images.100y.com.tw/pdf_file/23-AVAGO-HCPL-3120,J312,HCNW3120.pdf&quot;&gt;HCPL-3120&lt;/a&gt; as the higher current capacity gate drive and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ti.com/lit/ds/symlink/sg2524.pdf?HQS=TI-null-null-alldatasheets-df-pf-SEP-wwe&quot;&gt;SG3542&lt;/a&gt; as the function generator. The HCPL chip is a standard gate drive chip and the SG3542 provides an easy interface to set the frequency and duty cycle independently. After making these changes to the design of our Boost convertor, we obtain the below cleaner waveforms. There continue to be some large stray transients that need to be done away with before use in a real convertor. After making some more changes, tweaking the values and ratings of some circuit components we ended up making the Boost convertor work. The details are available in our &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/docs/DD08_Design_Lab_report.pdf&quot;&gt;project report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;align: left; text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/transients.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; A correct switching waveform with large transients&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;flyback-convertor-and-transformer-design&quot;&gt;Flyback convertor and transformer design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than the choice of a Flyback convertor, a non-isolated Boost convertor with a voltage boost from 5V to 180V could have been used. However, since the power and data source is a single USB port on a computer, it is crucial that we keep the low voltage (LV) and high voltage (HV) sides electrically isolated from each other. The only way to do this would be to choose an isolated convertor.&lt;br /&gt;
Further, an isolated convertor like the Flyback has the advantage of being able to utilise the turns ratio of its transformer as the voltage step up component. The problem of a high step up of $\frac{180}{5} = 36$ times using a non-isolated Boost convertor can be illustrated by comparing the input to output transfer functions of the Boost and the Flyback convertors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Boost convertor has the input $V_i$ to output $V_o$ transfer function of 
\[V_o = \frac{V_i}{1-D}.\]
Where $D$ is the duty cycle (or the fraction time spent on). So for a step up of $36$ times an unsustainable $D$ of $\frac{35}{36}$ will be required. However, now we can consider the Flyback convertor topology used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;align: left; text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/simple_flyback.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; An isolated Flyback convertor &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the transformer present in the circuit, the transfer function is given by,
\[V_o = \frac{N_2}{N_1} \frac{D}{1-D} V_i.\]
Where $\frac{N_2}{N_1}$ is the turns ratio of the transformer in question. With a reasonably large turns ratio, little of the step up burden falls on the $D$ term thereby making for a reasonable duty cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transformer was the central component for the successful design of the flyback convertor. The design of the transformer was undertaken for a switching frequency of 100KHz. As a fun design exercise, we decided to create a transformer from scratch instead of outsourcing the task to a workshop. With help from research assistants from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ee.iitb.ac.in/web/research/labs/apel&quot;&gt;Applied Power Electronics Lab (APEL)&lt;/a&gt; we managed to achieve our goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This transformer needed to have one input winding for the 5V USB power source, and two output windings. One output winding would correspond to the 180V output to power the Nixie tubes. An additional isolated 5V power output was required by us to power the silicon on the High Voltage side (see &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/nixieClockController&quot;&gt;part 3&lt;/a&gt; for details). After completion, the specs of the transformer can be found in our &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/docs/DD08_Design_Lab_report.pdf&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;. To complete the flyback convertor, the design we came up with initially was as follows,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;align: left; text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/flyback1.png&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; 555 timer based Flyback convertor. 5V tertiary winding omitted &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Here the components on the HV side remain similar to the earlier boost convertor. The key difference being that they are rated for suitably high voltages. The switching signal of a 100KHz square wave is provided to the MOSFET directly from a 555 timer. The duty cycle (which controls $D$) and the frequency of the 555 timer can be controlled using individual potentiometers in this design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A problem with this design is similar to the problem with driving a MOSFET gate with an analog function generator. The current that can be drawn from the output of the 555 timer is limited since the 555 chip is designed as a timer or perhaps a signal generator. In the design of the power supply, this problem manifests itself in the large switching losses that arise within the MOSFET switch. As can be seen in the figure depicting the switching of the IRFZ44N MOSFET when driven through an AFG, poor switching quality leads to a longer transition period between the on and off states. This causes significantly more heat loss in accordance with Joule’s law of heating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This problem was solved by sandwiching the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ti.com/lit/ds/symlink/ucc27321.pdf?ts=1594923781813&amp;amp;ref_url=https%253A%252F%252Fwww.google.com%252F&quot;&gt;UC37322&lt;/a&gt; gate driver between the 555 timer and the MOSFET gate. This allowed for a much better switching waveform thereby reducing the heating and energy loss from the IRFZ44N significantly. The last problem that remains to be solved is that of over voltage at the output side under no load conditions. This problem must be solved since in the absence of control on the output, the voltage would go increasing indefinitely damaging the circuit components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;feedback-control-of-output-voltage&quot;&gt;Feedback Control of Output Voltage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the switching action in a boost convertor is turned off, the output voltage ceases to build up. In such a case in the absence of any output load, the output voltage would not decrease or increase but rather remain constant. This situation may not be ideal but is still better than the voltage going on increasing indefinitely. The easiest way to shut off switching in our design would be to use the reset pin on the 555 timer generating the switching waveform. Another factor is that we must keep the reset signal of the 555 timer on the LV side and the voltage feedback signal on the HV side isolated from each other. This is achieved using opto-coupler signal isolation using an &lt;a href=&quot;https://projectpoint.in/datasheets/pdf/mct2e.pdf&quot;&gt;MCT2E&lt;/a&gt; between the two sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The details of the feedback mechanism can be found in the lower half of the below schematic. The mechanism for how this feedback works is quite interesting. An &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ti.com/lit/ds/snosc16d/snosc16d.pdf&quot;&gt;LM324&lt;/a&gt; opamp is configured as a comparator with the regulated 5V power supply intended for HV side silicon connected to the ‘+’ terminal of the comparator and a voltage divided version of the 180V (called VFB) output connected to the ‘-‘ terminal of the comparator. When VFB becomes too large, the output of the comparator turns off, thereby turning the output of the MCT2E phototransistor off which in turn resets the 555 timer output through the active low RESET pin. This RESET state remains the situation until the output voltage at the HV side drops below a certain threshold. Once the voltage drops by enough the phototransistor turns on again starting the switching action and the voltage gain. In the absence of a real load, this on-off procedure would continue cyclically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;align: left; text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Discrete_Schematic.png&quot; width=&quot;700px&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; The final and complete schematic of the power supply &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
More details about the circuit board layout with SMPS best practices and details about the creating tertiary winding of the transformer can be found in our &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/docs/DD08_Design_Lab_report.pdf&quot;&gt;project report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be appropriate to add here that though the feedback mechanism was tested on our earlier breadboard based design, it did not function correctly when placed within the final circuit board. Primarily, this had to do with the additional 5V power source from the tertiary winding of our transformer not functioning correctly. Hence the unused feedback stage is seen in the image at the start. Importantly, this makes the final power supply &lt;strong&gt;unsafe&lt;/strong&gt; to use without a load connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mr. Joginder Yadav, RA Machines Lab, IIT Bombay provided immense help for the design of the power supply and other modules of this project&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This project was completed in partial fulfilment of the requirements for EE 344: Electronic Design Lab at IITB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A more detailed description of the project along with schematics can be found in our &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/docs/DD08_Design_Lab_report.pdf&quot;&gt;project report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A demonstration of our project can be &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/MN-FbMPmbiw&quot;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Personal Reading List</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/nowReading" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Personal Reading List" /><published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/reading</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/nowReading">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Last updated: 14 Aug 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐ = Strongly Recommended&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐ = Recommended&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;⭐ ⭐ ⭐ = Enjoyable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;⭐ ⭐ = Not Recommended&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;⭐ = Steer Clear&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;📖 = Now Reading/Last Read&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;📕 = To be read&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;academic--textbooks&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Academic / Textbooks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optimal Control - Dan Liberzon 📖&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bayesian Networks - Judea Pearl 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bandits and Online learning - Tor Lattimore 📖&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Causality - Judea Pearl 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI: A Modern Approach - Peter Norvig and Stuart Russell 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reinforcement Learning 📖&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Convex Optimization - Lieven Vandenberghe and Stephen P. Boyd 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heuristics: Intelligent Search Strategies for Computer Problem Solving - Judea Pearl 📕&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;biographiesautobiographies&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Biographies/Autobiographies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Elon Musk - Ashlee Vance&lt;br /&gt;
⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;iCon, Steve Jobs - Jeffrey S. Young, Jeffrey Young, and William L. Simon&lt;br /&gt;
⭐ ⭐ ⭐&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Google Story - David A. Vise and Mark Malseed&lt;br /&gt;
⭐ ⭐ ⭐&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Everything Store - Brad Stone 📕&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;non-fiction&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non Fiction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Periodic Tales - Hugh Aldersey-Williams&lt;br /&gt;
⭐ ⭐ ⭐&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weapons of Math destruction - Cathy O’Neil&lt;br /&gt;
⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sapiens - YNH &lt;br /&gt;
⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Homo Deus - YNH &lt;br /&gt;
⭐ ⭐ ⭐&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Selfish Gene - Richard Dawkins &lt;br /&gt;
⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thinking fast and slow - Daniel Kahnman  &lt;br /&gt;
⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;21 lessons for the 21st century - YNH &lt;br /&gt;
⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You are a Badass - Jen Sincero  &lt;br /&gt;
⭐ ⭐&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The power of habit - Charles Duhigg &lt;br /&gt; 
⭐ ⭐ ⭐&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deep Work - Cal Newport &lt;br /&gt;
⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Extended phenotype - Richard Dawkins 📖&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enlightenment Now - Steven Pinker 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think and Grow Rich - Napoleon Hill 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Science of Getting Rich - Wallace Wattles 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Machines Who Think - Pamela McCorduck 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Brief History of Time - Stephen Hawking 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Emperor’s New Mind - Roger Penrose and follow up by Stuart Hameroff 📕
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Do anesthetics (gas) affect the microtubules directly. Is this a special chemical process?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This thread seeks a connection between Quantum mechanics and consciousness&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cycles of time - Roger Penrose 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shadows of the mind - Roger Penrose 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The road to reality - Roger Penrose 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creation Revisited - Peter Atkins (Yes the Chemist) 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Origin of species - Darwin 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dark Universe - Galouye 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Einstein’s Dreams - Alan Littman 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communist Manifesto - Marx and Engels 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Free to choose - Milton Freidman 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Wealth of Nations - Adam Smith 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One, Two, Three…Infinity - George Gamow (A Physicist) 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reflections on Language - Noam Chomsky 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Blind Watchmaker - Richard Dawkins 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ever since Darwin - Steven J Gould 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Books by the George A. Miller 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What everybody is saying - Joe Navarro 📕
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Non verbal cues/language&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Second World War - Winston Churchill 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Masters of Doom - David Kushner 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Code Complete - Steve McConnel - Software Development 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ikigai - Hector Garcia 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Love and Math - Edward Frenkel 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Book of Why - Judea Pearl 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Emperor of All Maladies - Siddhartha Mukherjee 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To save everything click here - Evgeny Morozov 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brave new world - Aldous Huxley 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rapt: Attention and the focussed life - Winifred Gallagher 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All things shining - Hubert Dreyfus, Sean Dorrance Kelly 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flow: The Psychology of Optimal Experience - Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Essays on Indic History - Vijender Sharma 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Future of the Mind - Michio Kaku 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Something Deeply Hidden - Sean Carroll 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Big Picture - Sean Carrol 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Ethical Algorithm - Aaron Roth and Michael Kearns 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Universe and the Teacup - K. C. Cole 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to Win Friends and Influence People - Dale Carnegie 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Homo Ludens - Johan Huizinga 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Double Helix - James Watson 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Road to Reality - Roger Penrose 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On Intelligence - Jeff Hawkins and Sandra Blakeslee 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Intelligence Trap - David Robinson 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Basic Laws of Human Stupidity - Carlo Cipolla 📕&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fiction&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fiction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Hitchhiker’s Guide to the Galaxy Omnibus: A Trilogy in Five Parts - Adams, Douglas&lt;br /&gt; 
⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Machine Stops - Short story by E. M. Forster &lt;br /&gt;
⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐ ⭐&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;मानसरोवर - प्रेमचंद 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solaris - Stanislaw Lem 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Black Cloud - Hoyle 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simulacron-3 - Galouye 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A for Andromeda - Fred Hoyle 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Books by Arthur C Clarke 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Americanah - Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;War of the Worlds - H.G. Wells 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shiva Trilogy - Amish Tripathi 📕&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Suheldev - Amish Tripathi 📕&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Last updated: 14 Aug 2020</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nixie Tube Characterization</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/nixieClock" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nixie Tube Characterization" /><published>2020-06-16T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-06-16T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/nixie-clock</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/nixieClock">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nixie_clock_no_bg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nixie clock&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is Part 1 in a three part series on our design of a USB powered Nixie Tube Clock display. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/nixieClockPower&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt; discusses the design of the power supply that steps up 5V to 170V. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/nixieClockController&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt; describes the design of a circuit which controls the display using isolated control signals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;nixie-tube-what-is-that&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nixie Tube. What is that?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&quot;right&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/single_tube.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nixie clock&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nixie tubes are Cold Cathode display tubes that light up when a high voltage is applied across them. The source of the illumination is electronic excitation and de-excitation. This mechanism is similar to the one used by more modern Neon Display tubes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Present day display technology, right from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.electronics-tutorials.ws/blog/7-segment-display-tutorial.html&quot;&gt;7 segment displays&lt;/a&gt; to LCD screens work by making multiple independent sources light up in a synchronized manner. A Nixie tube is different in that it has the shapes of all digits 0-9 present as separate cathodes. The digit(s) corresponding to the grounded cathode lights up with a beautiful yellow color. For this reason, a typical Nixie tube has at least 12 pins. 10 Cathodes each for the digits 0-9, one cathode for a decimal point and 1 Anode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information on Nixie Tubes and their working see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.explainthatstuff.com/how-nixie-tubes-work.html&quot;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nixie Tubes were a leading digit display technology during the 1970s - 80s. Nowadays, these displays are admired and valued for their Retro (Classic) look. Nixie Tube clocks have been a popular hobby project for many years now. Most of these projects use rectified AC mains as their power source. They do so since, the tubes have a somewhat high operating voltage of (about) 170V DC. What makes our project unique is that it succeeds in powering up the Nixie Clock Display using only a single 5V USB power supply. To know more about how our power supply does this, see &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/nixieClockPower&quot;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt; of this series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The limitation of using USB as our power source lead to another challenge; the power available through the host Single Board Computers USB port is not enough to light up numerous Nixie Tube units simultaneously. Multiplexing is a solution commonly employed in displays to save on power. It works by rapidly turning display units on and off in sequence making sure that only a single one glows at a time. Multiplexing takes advantage of the persistence of human vision to make it seem like all displays are turned on at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To check if the power budget problem could be overcome it was necessary to understand the I-V characteristics of the Nixie tubes. We had at our disposal, some now off-market, Nixie Tubes by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bharat_Electronics_Limited&quot;&gt;Bharat Electronics Limited&lt;/a&gt; (BEL) which were loaned to us by our advisor &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ee.iitb.ac.in/~mukul/&quot;&gt;Mukul Chandorkar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;i--v-characteristics&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I- V characteristics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&quot;right&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/figure2.png&quot; alt=&quot;nixie clock&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the absence of available documentation on our BEL tubes, we performed our own characterization experiments which are described here. The I-V characteristics of the tubes were quite necessary for the design of our power supply. &lt;br /&gt; 
This is the case since the feasibility of powering the clock from a computers USB port must first be assessed. Moreover details like the peak current drawn are essential for the design of the transformer in the isolated power supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The I-V characteristics for the digits 2 and 7 are shown to the right. Some observations here are-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The current requirement at a particular operating voltage point varies slightly from digit to digit
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This was expected due to physicial difference between the shapes of the two cathodes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The characteristics of the Nixie Tube are somewhat similar to that of a diode
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Current picks up rapidly as voltage is increased and soon current starts to increase rapidly for small increases in voltage&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This also highlights the importance of the presence of a series resistance while operating these tubes since there is no significant internal resistance&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This characterization was done using a full bridge rectifier, an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autotransformer&quot;&gt;autotransformer&lt;/a&gt; connected to AC mains and a small circuit board with a filter capacitance, a capacitor discharge pathway (for when power is turned off, indicator LED also present) and a series resistance. Readers familiar with electronics would recognize this as the standard AC-DC conversion circuit. Two multimeters were used to act as voltmeter and ammeter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;power-budgeting&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Power Budgeting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The voltage level available from USB is &lt;strong&gt;5V&lt;/strong&gt; as is well known. The maximum current that a single USB port can be expected to provide is &lt;strong&gt;500mA&lt;/strong&gt;. This caps the available power at approximately &lt;strong&gt;2.5W&lt;/strong&gt;. As seen in the previous section, a single tube draws about &lt;strong&gt;10mA&lt;/strong&gt; of current at &lt;strong&gt;150V&lt;/strong&gt; glowing very brightly, thus requiring &lt;strong&gt;1.5W&lt;/strong&gt; approximately. Hence as it can be seen, the there isn’t much margin for inefficiency in the design of the power supply, but designing one is certainly feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;experiments-with-a-faulty-tube&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experiments with a Faulty Tube&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/collate.png&quot; alt=&quot;I- V char&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an initial experiment we blew out the 0 digit of a Nixie Tube due to our faulty method of recording its I-V characteristics. We didn’t include with the tube a current limiting series resistor. This caused a current overload through the 0 digit cathode rendering it useless. This tube is referred to as partially faulty (PF).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thought it would be an interesting exercise to observe if a problem with one cathode affected the I-V characteristics of any other digit. Based on comparisons with the data from the correct tube mentioned above, and the plot on the right comparing I-V characteristics for digit 6, we can conclude that damage to one digit’s cathode does not affect the performance of other digits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hysterisis&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hysterisis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/hyst.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hyst1&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/figure6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hyst2&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the forward I-V characteristics (Increasing voltage) we also performed retreating I-V characteristics. The retreating characteristics involved decreasing the voltage down from the highest V reading to the turn off voltage. We were inclined to document this behaviour since the tubes were seen showing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hysteresis&quot;&gt;Hysteresis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that the current requirement for a particular digit can be different depending on whether we are moving forward from the turn on voltage or decreasing the voltage applied. That being said, the current difference is quite low, in the (μA) range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;precious-tubes-need-holders&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Precious Tubes need Holders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/holders.png&quot; alt=&quot;holders schematic&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nixie Tubes are something of a novelty. So to keep the option of using these tubes in another project open, we wanted to make them socketable. On failing to find a viable off the shelf solution we decided to design our own tube holders as small PCBs with pin heads plugging onto the main controller board. The design is pictured above and the real life finished product is pictured below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/tube_holder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;holders&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the tubes are noticeably bent and crooked on these holders. The reason for this was that the legs of the tubes were quite fragile and even a small amount of strain to the leg-glass joint could potentially break the terminal off. So, after breaking a leg on one of our spare tubes, we didn’t try bending the legs of any of the tubes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This project was completed in partial fulfilment of the requirements for EE 344: Electronic Design Lab at IITB&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A more detailed description of the project along with schematics can be found in our &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/docs/DD08_Design_Lab_report.pdf&quot;&gt;project report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A demonstration of our project can be &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/MN-FbMPmbiw&quot;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">scriptTest</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/scriptTest" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="scriptTest" /><published>2020-06-04T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-06-04T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/scriptTest</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/scriptTest">&lt;html xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml&quot;&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;meta http-equiv=&quot;Content-Type&quot; content=&quot;text/html; charset=utf-8&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;meta http-equiv=&quot;Content-Style-Type&quot; content=&quot;text/css&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;meta name=&quot;generator&quot; content=&quot;pandoc&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;R12/Ishank Juneja/16D070012&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;code{white-space: pre;}&lt;/style&gt;
  &lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS_CHTML-full&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;h1 class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;R12/Ishank Juneja/16D070012&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the classic Markov Decision Process (MDP) setup, we associate a tuple &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\((S, A, T, R)\)&lt;/span&gt; with every MDP. In this notation, &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(S\)&lt;/span&gt; is the set of states the agent can take, &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(A\)&lt;/span&gt; is the set of possible actions for the agent, &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(T:S \times A \rightarrow \Pi(s)\)&lt;/span&gt; is the state transition function of the problem. &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(T\)&lt;/span&gt; specifies the probability distribution over next states &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(s&amp;#39; \in S\)&lt;/span&gt; on taking an action &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(a \in A\)&lt;/span&gt; starting from state &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(s \in S\)&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(R\)&lt;/span&gt; is the reward function which can be viewed as a feedback on agent performance from the environment. An assumption implicit to this model is the observability of state &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(s \in S\)&lt;/span&gt;. Often times, it is not the case that an agent has access to its exact state. Instead, the agent might only have access to an observation &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(o \in \Omega\)&lt;/span&gt; which captures incomplete information about its underlying state. This framework satisfactorily models many practical situations. For instance, consider a robot that is attempting to localize its position (directly unobservable state &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(s\)&lt;/span&gt;) in a multi-storied building by merely looking at a particular intersection in a corridor (observation &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(o\)&lt;/span&gt;). Partially Observable MDPs (POMDPs) provide a richer mathematical framework which is able to describe many such situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pomdp-framework&quot; class=&quot;unnumbered&quot;&gt;The POMDP Framework&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A POMDP is completely described by the tuple &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\((S, A, T, R, \Omega, O)\)&lt;/span&gt;, where&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\((S, A, T, R)\)&lt;/span&gt; is the underlying MDP, &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\Omega\)&lt;/span&gt; is a finite set of observations the agent can experience and &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(O:S \times A \rightarrow \Pi(\Omega)\)&lt;/span&gt; is the observation function which gives, for every state and action, a probability distribution over possible observations. Under the POMDP framework an agent is unable to discern its state accurately. Instead of the true state, the agent makes “an observation” &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(o\)&lt;/span&gt; based on the action &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; taken and the (still unobserved) resulting state &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(s&amp;#39;\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
An implication of this limitation is that an agent wishing to act optimally must use its memory of all previous actions and observations. To simplify the problem, the POMDP model introduces a &lt;em&gt;belief state&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt;. Belief states are probability distributions over the true underlying states of the agent. That is, for each state &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(s\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b(s)\)&lt;/span&gt; gives the probability of the agent being in that state. By design, the agents belief state at any point of time is a sufficient statistic (SS) for all its previous experience. As a SS, the belief states capture all the past observations and the belief state that the agent started with. Sequential decision-making in the POMDP becomes Markovian in belief state &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt; due to the SS property.&lt;br /&gt;
To compute and update belief states as new experience is accumulated, the agent includes a block known as the state-estimator (SE). More precisely, given an observation &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(o\)&lt;/span&gt;, the action taken &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; and the previous belief state &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt;, the SE is the function SE&lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\((b, a, o)\)&lt;/span&gt; which outputs the new belief state &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b&amp;#39;\)&lt;/span&gt;. Using the rules of conditional probability and the definitions of the POMDP parameters, the paper derives the relation &lt;span class=&quot;math display&quot;&gt;\[b&amp;#39;(s&amp;#39;) \propto O(s&amp;#39;, a, o)\sum_{s \in S}T(s, a, s&amp;#39;)b(s),\]&lt;/span&gt; where the probabilities in &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b&amp;#39;\)&lt;/span&gt; are computed using the constraint &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\sum_{s \in S}b(s) = 1\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
The other necessary component to describe a POMDP agent is the policy being followed by it. In the POMDP framework, a policy maps a belief state vector &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt; to an action &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt;. Since the problem is Markovian in the belief state &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt;, obtaining a policy through POMDP planning is equivalent to solving the planning problem for an associated &lt;strong&gt;belief MDP&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
The parameters for the belief MDP are described below,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{B}\)&lt;/span&gt; is the set of possible belief states and forms the state space&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The set of actions &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(A\)&lt;/span&gt; remains the same as the POMDP&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\tau(b,a,b&amp;#39;)\)&lt;/span&gt; is the state-transition function which can be computed using the POMDP parameters&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\rho(b, a)\)&lt;/span&gt; is the reward function and is given by an expectation over the reward function &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(R(s, a)\)&lt;/span&gt; under the distribution over states given by &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b(s)\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;planning-for-pomdps&quot; class=&quot;unnumbered&quot;&gt;Planning for POMDPs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is often intractable to solve the planning problem for continuous state MDPs, however the special structure of the belief MDP lends it properties that give rise to efficient planning algorithms. In this paper the authors focus primarily on two planning approaches - &lt;strong&gt;Exhaustive Enumeration and Witness Algorithm&lt;/strong&gt; the latter among which is a novel approach. Both methods provide a means to determine the optimal &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(t\)&lt;/span&gt; - step value function &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(V_t\)&lt;/span&gt; given a start belief state &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt;. Here &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(t\)&lt;/span&gt; - step refers to the situation where there are only &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(t\)&lt;/span&gt; steps remaining in the agents lifetime. The paper considers the more general finite horizon problem since an infinite horizon discounted trajectory can always be approximated to arbitrary precision by a long enough finite trajectory. Lastly, once the optimal value function is computed using Value-Iteration, it is a straightforward task to determine the optimal policy to complete planning.&lt;br /&gt;
Next, the paper describes how a &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(t\)&lt;/span&gt;-step policy can be represented using a &lt;em&gt;policy tree&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(p\)&lt;/span&gt; of depth &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(t\)&lt;/span&gt;. An expression for the expected return &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(V_p(s)\)&lt;/span&gt; associated with executing the policy &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(p\)&lt;/span&gt;, starting from a state &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(s\)&lt;/span&gt;, can be derived using the belief MDP parameters. However, the actual quantity of interest is the return for a given &lt;em&gt;belief state&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt;. Using the linearity of expectations we have, &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(V_p(b) = \sum_{s \in S} b(s) V_p(s)\)&lt;/span&gt;. Treating &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(V_p\)&lt;/span&gt; as vectors of length &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(|S|\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(V_p\)&lt;/span&gt; becomes a dot product.&lt;br /&gt;
The objective of planning through value-iteration is to obtain &lt;span class=&quot;math display&quot;&gt;\[V_t(b) = \max_{p \in \mathcal{P}} b \cdot V_p.\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;pruning-the-search-space&quot; class=&quot;unnumbered&quot;&gt;Pruning the Search space&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using geometrical arguments the authors were able to show that the optimal value function &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(V_t\)&lt;/span&gt; is piecewise linear and convex. Such a &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(V_t\)&lt;/span&gt; induces a partition on the space of possible belief states such that for every &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt; there exists an optimal policy tree. While iterating over value functions, we would be much better of if our search space were as compact as possible. To do achieve this, we keep only &lt;em&gt;useful&lt;/em&gt; policy trees and prune way the others. A policy tree &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(p&amp;#39;\)&lt;/span&gt; is considered useful if its value function &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(V_{p&amp;#39;}\)&lt;/span&gt; is such that it cannot be dominated everywhere by the maximum of the value functions of any subset of &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{P}\)&lt;/span&gt;. A possible way of ensuring that we have a minimal subset is to ensure that for every policy, there is at least one point in the state space where its own value function dominates. Once a minimal representation (set of policies) &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{V}_t\)&lt;/span&gt; for the optimal value function &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(V_t\)&lt;/span&gt; is obtained, value iteration (VI) can be applied to the problem in a manner identical to that of VI for &lt;strong&gt;discrete&lt;/strong&gt; MDPs.&lt;br /&gt;
The only problem left to be solved then is that of obtaining a minimal representation of the &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(t\)&lt;/span&gt; step optimal value function given a minimal representation of the &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(t-1\)&lt;/span&gt; step value function &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(V_{t-1}\)&lt;/span&gt;. The next two algorithms achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;exhaustive-enumeration&quot; class=&quot;unnumbered&quot;&gt;Exhaustive Enumeration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This algorithm works by constructing a superset &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{V}_t^{+}\)&lt;/span&gt; of the minimal set and then pruning it down to &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{V}_t\)&lt;/span&gt;. The algorithm can be broken down into two steps - generation and pruning. To generate the superset &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{V}_t^{+}\)&lt;/span&gt;, we only need to consider the policy trees contained in &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{V}_{t-1}\)&lt;/span&gt; since a policy with a non-useful subtree cannot itself be useful. This means that the superset will contain &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(|A||\mathcal{V}_{t-1}|^{\Omega}\)&lt;/span&gt; elements.&lt;br /&gt;
To prune the superset, we can identify the optimal parent &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(t\)&lt;/span&gt; length policy for each &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(t-1\)&lt;/span&gt; length sub-policy using linear programming. For this we would need to compute the value functions for each of the policy trees in &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{V}_t^{+}\)&lt;/span&gt;. This can be done efficiently using the value functions of the sub-trees.&lt;br /&gt;
The main drawback of this approach is that we need to go through the superset &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{V}_t^{+}\)&lt;/span&gt; which has a size exponential in the number of possible observations &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(|\Omega|\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;witness-algorithm---authors-novel-approach&quot; class=&quot;unnumbered&quot;&gt;Witness Algorithm - Authors’ Novel Approach&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of computing &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{V}_t\)&lt;/span&gt; directly, the witness algorithm computes a set &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{Q}_t^{a}\)&lt;/span&gt; for every action &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{Q}_t^{a}\)&lt;/span&gt; represents the set of all &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(t\)&lt;/span&gt; step policy trees with the action &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; at their root. The set &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{V}_t\)&lt;/span&gt; is then computed by pruning the union of such policies trees - &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\cup_a \mathcal{Q}_t^{a}\)&lt;/span&gt;. The job of the witness algorithm is to provide an &lt;em&gt;efficient&lt;/em&gt; technique to compute &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{Q}_t^{a}\)&lt;/span&gt;. In particular the authors show that their algorithm has complexity polynomial in &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(|S|,|A|,|\Omega|,|\mathcal{V}_{t-1}|\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(|\mathcal{Q}_t^{a}|\)&lt;/span&gt;. A caveat here is that &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(|\mathcal{Q}_t^{a}|\)&lt;/span&gt; can be exponentially larger than the size of &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{V}_t\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
The core of the witness algorithm lies in its pruning technique. The algorithm starts of with a single policy tree optimal for some arbitrary belief state &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt;. Then we check if there exists a belief state &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt; for which the &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(Q\)&lt;/span&gt; value estimated using our current set of trees - &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\hat{\mathcal{Q}}_{t}^{a}(b)\)&lt;/span&gt; is less than the true &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(Q\)&lt;/span&gt; value given by &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{Q}_{t}^{a}(b)\)&lt;/span&gt;. Such a &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt; is said to serve as a &lt;em&gt;witness&lt;/em&gt; to the fact that our current collection of policy trees is incomplete. Once such a witness is identified, the algorithm appends the policy, with action &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; at the root, that yields the best value for the earlier chosen belief state &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt;. This process continues until no more witness points exist and we conclude that our representation of &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(Q\)&lt;/span&gt; is perfect. Since the belief space is continuous, the search for witnesses &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt; is achieved using linear programming.&lt;br /&gt;
The witness algorithm fails to perform well on problems where &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(|\mathcal{Q}_t^{a}|\)&lt;/span&gt; is “not polynomial&amp;quot;. In such situations the authors point to other algorithms such as the briefly described &lt;em&gt;linear support algorithm&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;obtaining-a-minimal-finite-state-controller&quot; class=&quot;unnumbered&quot;&gt;Obtaining a Minimal Finite State Controller&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some special POMDP problems, the optimal policy trees have the property that the observation-action mapping at every level remains the same. In such situations the policy becomes stationary and can be represented as a more compact plan-graph. The way a plan graph is created, on every step an agent could start of in the node optimal for its initial belief state and thereafter simply make observations and follow the arc associated with the observation to the next node. This picture is essentially that of a finite state controller which uses the minimal possible amount of memory to act optimally in a POMDP environment. As the paper points out, it is fascinating that the POMDP problem started off as a discrete problem, was converted to a continuous belief space and at the end the continuous solution could again be mapped back to a discrete controller.&lt;br /&gt;
Some questions I have are -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What exactly is the efficient pruning strategy for obtaining the minimal useful set &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{V}\)&lt;/span&gt; of policy trees? It seemed to me that we can’t do without ensuring that every policy we throw out does not dominate all other policies for some &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(b \in \mathcal{B}\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the description of the witness algorithm (WA), the authors claim that the running time of WA is polynomial if &lt;span class=&quot;math inline&quot;&gt;\(|\mathcal{Q}_t^{a}|\)&lt;/span&gt; is polynomial. What is meant by the latter being polynomial? What problem parameters are being refereed to?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">R12/Ishank Juneja/16D070012 R12/Ishank Juneja/16D070012 Introduction Under the classic Markov Decision Process (MDP) setup, we associate a tuple \((S, A, T, R)\) with every MDP. In this notation, \(S\) is the set of states the agent can take, \(A\) is the set of possible actions for the agent, \(T:S \times A \rightarrow \Pi(s)\) is the state transition function of the problem. \(T\) specifies the probability distribution over next states \(s&amp;#39; \in S\) on taking an action \(a \in A\) starting from state \(s \in S\). \(R\) is the reward function which can be viewed as a feedback on agent performance from the environment. An assumption implicit to this model is the observability of state \(s \in S\). Often times, it is not the case that an agent has access to its exact state. Instead, the agent might only have access to an observation \(o \in \Omega\) which captures incomplete information about its underlying state. This framework satisfactorily models many practical situations. For instance, consider a robot that is attempting to localize its position (directly unobservable state \(s\)) in a multi-storied building by merely looking at a particular intersection in a corridor (observation \(o\)). Partially Observable MDPs (POMDPs) provide a richer mathematical framework which is able to describe many such situations. The POMDP Framework A POMDP is completely described by the tuple \((S, A, T, R, \Omega, O)\), where \((S, A, T, R)\) is the underlying MDP, \(\Omega\) is a finite set of observations the agent can experience and \(O:S \times A \rightarrow \Pi(\Omega)\) is the observation function which gives, for every state and action, a probability distribution over possible observations. Under the POMDP framework an agent is unable to discern its state accurately. Instead of the true state, the agent makes “an observation” \(o\) based on the action \(a\) taken and the (still unobserved) resulting state \(s&amp;#39;\). An implication of this limitation is that an agent wishing to act optimally must use its memory of all previous actions and observations. To simplify the problem, the POMDP model introduces a belief state \(b\). Belief states are probability distributions over the true underlying states of the agent. That is, for each state \(s\), \(b(s)\) gives the probability of the agent being in that state. By design, the agents belief state at any point of time is a sufficient statistic (SS) for all its previous experience. As a SS, the belief states capture all the past observations and the belief state that the agent started with. Sequential decision-making in the POMDP becomes Markovian in belief state \(b\) due to the SS property. To compute and update belief states as new experience is accumulated, the agent includes a block known as the state-estimator (SE). More precisely, given an observation \(o\), the action taken \(a\) and the previous belief state \(b\), the SE is the function SE\((b, a, o)\) which outputs the new belief state \(b&amp;#39;\). Using the rules of conditional probability and the definitions of the POMDP parameters, the paper derives the relation \[b&amp;#39;(s&amp;#39;) \propto O(s&amp;#39;, a, o)\sum_{s \in S}T(s, a, s&amp;#39;)b(s),\] where the probabilities in \(b&amp;#39;\) are computed using the constraint \(\sum_{s \in S}b(s) = 1\). The other necessary component to describe a POMDP agent is the policy being followed by it. In the POMDP framework, a policy maps a belief state vector \(b\) to an action \(a\). Since the problem is Markovian in the belief state \(b\), obtaining a policy through POMDP planning is equivalent to solving the planning problem for an associated belief MDP. The parameters for the belief MDP are described below, \(\mathcal{B}\) is the set of possible belief states and forms the state space The set of actions \(A\) remains the same as the POMDP \(\tau(b,a,b&amp;#39;)\) is the state-transition function which can be computed using the POMDP parameters \(\rho(b, a)\) is the reward function and is given by an expectation over the reward function \(R(s, a)\) under the distribution over states given by \(b(s)\) Planning for POMDPs It is often intractable to solve the planning problem for continuous state MDPs, however the special structure of the belief MDP lends it properties that give rise to efficient planning algorithms. In this paper the authors focus primarily on two planning approaches - Exhaustive Enumeration and Witness Algorithm the latter among which is a novel approach. Both methods provide a means to determine the optimal \(t\) - step value function \(V_t\) given a start belief state \(b\). Here \(t\) - step refers to the situation where there are only \(t\) steps remaining in the agents lifetime. The paper considers the more general finite horizon problem since an infinite horizon discounted trajectory can always be approximated to arbitrary precision by a long enough finite trajectory. Lastly, once the optimal value function is computed using Value-Iteration, it is a straightforward task to determine the optimal policy to complete planning. Next, the paper describes how a \(t\)-step policy can be represented using a policy tree - \(p\) of depth \(t\). An expression for the expected return \(V_p(s)\) associated with executing the policy \(p\), starting from a state \(s\), can be derived using the belief MDP parameters. However, the actual quantity of interest is the return for a given belief state \(b\). Using the linearity of expectations we have, \(V_p(b) = \sum_{s \in S} b(s) V_p(s)\). Treating \(b\) and \(V_p\) as vectors of length \(|S|\), \(V_p\) becomes a dot product. The objective of planning through value-iteration is to obtain \[V_t(b) = \max_{p \in \mathcal{P}} b \cdot V_p.\] Pruning the Search space Using geometrical arguments the authors were able to show that the optimal value function \(V_t\) is piecewise linear and convex. Such a \(V_t\) induces a partition on the space of possible belief states such that for every \(b\) there exists an optimal policy tree. While iterating over value functions, we would be much better of if our search space were as compact as possible. To do achieve this, we keep only useful policy trees and prune way the others. A policy tree \(p&amp;#39;\) is considered useful if its value function \(V_{p&amp;#39;}\) is such that it cannot be dominated everywhere by the maximum of the value functions of any subset of \(\mathcal{P}\). A possible way of ensuring that we have a minimal subset is to ensure that for every policy, there is at least one point in the state space where its own value function dominates. Once a minimal representation (set of policies) \(\mathcal{V}_t\) for the optimal value function \(V_t\) is obtained, value iteration (VI) can be applied to the problem in a manner identical to that of VI for discrete MDPs. The only problem left to be solved then is that of obtaining a minimal representation of the \(t\) step optimal value function given a minimal representation of the \(t-1\) step value function \(V_{t-1}\). The next two algorithms achieve this. Exhaustive Enumeration This algorithm works by constructing a superset \(\mathcal{V}_t^{+}\) of the minimal set and then pruning it down to \(\mathcal{V}_t\). The algorithm can be broken down into two steps - generation and pruning. To generate the superset \(\mathcal{V}_t^{+}\), we only need to consider the policy trees contained in \(\mathcal{V}_{t-1}\) since a policy with a non-useful subtree cannot itself be useful. This means that the superset will contain \(|A||\mathcal{V}_{t-1}|^{\Omega}\) elements. To prune the superset, we can identify the optimal parent \(t\) length policy for each \(t-1\) length sub-policy using linear programming. For this we would need to compute the value functions for each of the policy trees in \(\mathcal{V}_t^{+}\). This can be done efficiently using the value functions of the sub-trees. The main drawback of this approach is that we need to go through the superset \(\mathcal{V}_t^{+}\) which has a size exponential in the number of possible observations \(|\Omega|\). Witness Algorithm - Authors’ Novel Approach Instead of computing \(\mathcal{V}_t\) directly, the witness algorithm computes a set \(\mathcal{Q}_t^{a}\) for every action \(a\). \(\mathcal{Q}_t^{a}\) represents the set of all \(t\) step policy trees with the action \(a\) at their root. The set \(\mathcal{V}_t\) is then computed by pruning the union of such policies trees - \(\cup_a \mathcal{Q}_t^{a}\). The job of the witness algorithm is to provide an efficient technique to compute \(\mathcal{Q}_t^{a}\). In particular the authors show that their algorithm has complexity polynomial in \(|S|,|A|,|\Omega|,|\mathcal{V}_{t-1}|\) and \(|\mathcal{Q}_t^{a}|\). A caveat here is that \(|\mathcal{Q}_t^{a}|\) can be exponentially larger than the size of \(\mathcal{V}_t\). The core of the witness algorithm lies in its pruning technique. The algorithm starts of with a single policy tree optimal for some arbitrary belief state \(b\). Then we check if there exists a belief state \(b\) for which the \(Q\) value estimated using our current set of trees - \(\hat{\mathcal{Q}}_{t}^{a}(b)\) is less than the true \(Q\) value given by \(\mathcal{Q}_{t}^{a}(b)\). Such a \(b\) is said to serve as a witness to the fact that our current collection of policy trees is incomplete. Once such a witness is identified, the algorithm appends the policy, with action \(a\) at the root, that yields the best value for the earlier chosen belief state \(b\). This process continues until no more witness points exist and we conclude that our representation of \(Q\) is perfect. Since the belief space is continuous, the search for witnesses \(b\) is achieved using linear programming. The witness algorithm fails to perform well on problems where \(|\mathcal{Q}_t^{a}|\) is “not polynomial&amp;quot;. In such situations the authors point to other algorithms such as the briefly described linear support algorithm. Obtaining a Minimal Finite State Controller For some special POMDP problems, the optimal policy trees have the property that the observation-action mapping at every level remains the same. In such situations the policy becomes stationary and can be represented as a more compact plan-graph. The way a plan graph is created, on every step an agent could start of in the node optimal for its initial belief state and thereafter simply make observations and follow the arc associated with the observation to the next node. This picture is essentially that of a finite state controller which uses the minimal possible amount of memory to act optimally in a POMDP environment. As the paper points out, it is fascinating that the POMDP problem started off as a discrete problem, was converted to a continuous belief space and at the end the continuous solution could again be mapped back to a discrete controller. Some questions I have are - What exactly is the efficient pruning strategy for obtaining the minimal useful set \(\mathcal{V}\) of policy trees? It seemed to me that we can’t do without ensuring that every policy we throw out does not dominate all other policies for some \(b \in \mathcal{B}\). In the description of the witness algorithm (WA), the authors claim that the running time of WA is polynomial if \(|\mathcal{Q}_t^{a}|\) is polynomial. What is meant by the latter being polynomial? What problem parameters are being refereed to?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Webpage Setup using Jekyll</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/pageSetupJekyll" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Webpage Setup using Jekyll" /><published>2020-05-24T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-05-24T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/webpage-setup</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/pageSetupJekyll">&lt;p&gt;This post illustrates how to get a Jekyll static site up and running with some useful add-ons and tips. Rather than be a self contained post, this serves as more of a collection of pointers to other useful resources around the internet that when taken together get the job done.&lt;br /&gt;
The tutorial and linked instructions assume a linux system with a &lt;em&gt;bash shell&lt;/em&gt; available. Further familiarity with creating content for the Web with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.markdownguide.org/getting-started/&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; is assumed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lift-off&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lift Off!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When starting off making a personal webpage with Jekyll, the first place one might end up is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;official website&lt;/a&gt;. The Jekyll documentation is great for understanding its more advanced features but I found, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.taniarascia.com/make-a-static-website-with-jekyll/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; to be a much more self contained tutorial to getting a webpage up and running. In particular the official Jekyll documentation misses out on some of the details of creating some so called ‘gemfiles’ within the folder structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After completing the procedure in the linked tutorial, the directory structure we get looks as follows-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
├── 404.html
├── about.md
├── _config.yml
├── feed.xml
├── Gemfile
├── Gemfile.lock
├── index.md
├── _posts
│   └── 2019-07-16-welcome-to-jekyll.markdown
└── _site
    ├── 404.html
    ├── about
    │   └── index.html
    ├── assets
    │   ├── main.css
    │   └── minima-social-icons.svg
    ├── feed.xml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might gather from following the linked tutorial, when we run &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle exec jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt; (or just &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt; on some systems) in the outermost directory containing our project, a rendering of our webpage on the local URL &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:4000&quot;&gt;http://127.0.0.1:4000&lt;/a&gt; becomes avaiable. Or when we run &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle exec jekyll build&lt;/code&gt;, the finished webpage (or rather collection of pages) is placed into the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; directory from which it could be deployed onto our preferred web server. &lt;br /&gt;
The &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; directory is the finished product in some sense, so any changes made directly to the contents of this direcotry are pointless since these would be overwritten during the next compilation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;deploying-in-the-wild&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deploying in the Wild&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually when a jekyll based blog/webpage is setup, it is done on our own free &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Git-Hub-user-name.github.io&lt;/code&gt; domain name using &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;github pages&lt;/a&gt;, in which case we don’t need to worry about deploying the contents of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; ourselves, since github does that for us automatically when we push the entire outer directory and any subsequent changes to it to a specially named remote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;github pages&lt;/a&gt;, I also have experience with hosting a website on my university &lt;a href=&quot;http://home.iitb.ac.in/~ishankjuneja/&quot;&gt;academic homepage&lt;/a&gt;. In our universities case, students are allocated 1 GB of space on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://home.iitb.ac.in/&quot;&gt;BigHome&lt;/a&gt; cloud service. Also each student gets a domain name of the form &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://home.iitb.ac.in/~LDAPuserName&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cc.iitb.ac.in/page/personalwebpage&quot;&gt;procedure&lt;/a&gt; to make a student webpage work there is as follows&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Login on &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://home.iitb.ac.in/&lt;/code&gt; using your LDAP ID&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a repository named &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;public_html&lt;/code&gt; onto your drive space&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Place the contents of the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; directory compiled by Jekyll into the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;public_html&lt;/code&gt; repository and you’re done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of my university homepage I had some trouble making sense of the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;url&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;base_url&lt;/code&gt; field appearing in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt; file. The StackOverflow question I &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/52680191/forced-to-use-absolute-urls-in-jekyll&quot;&gt;asked here&lt;/a&gt; would clear up how the fields have to be set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;creating-and-placing-markdown-files&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating and Placing Markdown Files&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first page a visitor would see when they arrive at your website would be the contents of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;index.md&lt;/code&gt; Under the minima template the top right corner would contain links to pages rendered using any and every markdown file present in either the outermost project directory, in any specially named directory for instance, one called &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pages&lt;/code&gt;. Every other webpage, (blog posts, or any other format) should appear either inside the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory or any of its sub-directories (and so on recursively). Note that all markdown files present inside &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; must be named using the format &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-file-name&lt;/code&gt;, else the files won’t show up in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; finished product and by extension, will not be accessible from your website. Any &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; markdown files present anywhere outside of this prescribed template will be treated like a new page and would be added to the upper right corner navigation pane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the default &lt;em&gt;minima&lt;/em&gt; template, there are two options as far as the layout of a webpage generatred using a markdown file is concerned - &lt;strong&gt;post&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;page&lt;/strong&gt;. To me the difference between the two seems very minor with the post layout having an automatic date stamp at the top of the rendered document and the page layout (somewhat fortunately) lacking such a date feature. Note that the default behaviour of these templates can be changed or new templates to replace them can be created as explained in the section on overriding themes explains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;customizing-urls-using-permalinks&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Customizing URLs using Permalinks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another useful jekyll feature is that of &lt;em&gt;permalinks&lt;/em&gt;. By default, jekyll parses your file name for its date to create a URL, for instance, by default, the URL of this page would have been &lt;br /&gt; &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;https://ishank-juneja.github.io/2020/05/24/webpage-setup.html&lt;/code&gt;. If you, like me, find such a URL aesthetically displeasing, then you might want to look into &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=938jDG_YPdc&quot;&gt;permalinks&lt;/a&gt; in Jekyll.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title, date, permalink and other useful information go into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/front-matter/&quot;&gt;front-matter&lt;/a&gt; of the markdown file, for instance, the front matter for this page looks like so,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-markdown&quot; data-lang=&quot;markdown&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;---&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;post&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;2020-05-24&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;permalink&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;/blog/pageSetup&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Webpage Setup using Jekyll&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;---&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-picture-frame-surrounding-your-webpage&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Picture-Frame Surrounding Your Webpage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the bottom of every page on your static website, are little links to the owners email, twitter and potentially other places of online presence. The structure of this bottom bar is dependent entirely on our choice of template and cannot be altered without creating our own fork of the template or using some other pre-existing template. The contents of the bottom bar are controlled by the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt; file. The file for this web-page is given below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-yaml&quot; data-lang=&quot;yaml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Ishank's Webpage&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;full_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Ishank Juneja&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;email&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;ishankjuneja@gmail.com&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;email2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;ishankjuneja@iitb.ac.in&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;description&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# this means to ignore newlines until &quot;baseurl:&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Personal homepage: Ishank Juneja&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;https://ishank-juneja.github.io&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# the base hostname &amp;amp; protocol for your site, e.g. http://example.com&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;twitter_username&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;ishankjuneja&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;github_username&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;ishank-juneja&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;quora_username&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Ishank-Juneja&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;stackoverflow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;4477387/ishank-juneja&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;jekyll-mentions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;base_url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;https://github.com&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# Google Analytics&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;google_analytics&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;UA-166118550-1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;linkedin_username&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;ishank-juneja&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;include&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;_pages'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;footer-links-active&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;stackoverflow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# Build settings&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;markdown&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;kramdown&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;theme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;minima&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;plugins&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;jekyll-feed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The files that create this frame around each webpage are present in a so-called &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Gemfile&lt;/code&gt; and can be accessed and modified in the manner described in the next section. In an earlier version of Jekyll these files placed in specially named directories were accessible from the project directory by default. These concealed files consist of things like SVG files (for the GH icon, the twitter bird etc.)&lt;br /&gt;
The quick way to access these auxiliary files would be to refer to the source code of a pre-existing website. For instance, while making this webpage I refereed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/martiansideofthemoon/martiansideofthemoon.github.io&quot;&gt;this website&lt;/a&gt; which belongs to a former student here at IITB. His well desgined webpage also inspired me to add &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/help/flair&quot;&gt;stack exchange flair&lt;/a&gt; to the footer of my webpage. Perhaps the better way to access this directory structure would be to navigate to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Gemfile&lt;/code&gt; supporting the content. This is explained in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;overriding-themes&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overriding Themes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The files that help make the minima template are present in a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Gemfile&lt;/code&gt; (Ruby language terminology). To be able to modify any of the default behaviour of the minima template, we can navigate to the Gemfile directory for the minima theme by running &lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xdg-open $(bundle info --path minima)&lt;/code&gt; or&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd $(bundle info --path minima)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 
in a terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On navigating to the minima template source location a user would see the following files-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
├── assets
│   ├── main.scss
│   └── minima-social-icons.svg
├── _includes
│   ├── disqus_comments.html
│   ├── footer.html
│   ├── header.html
│   ├── head.html
│   ├── icon-github.html
│   ├── icon-github.svg
│   ├── icon-twitter.html
│   ├── icon-twitter.svg
│   └── social.html
├── _layouts
│   ├── default.html
│   ├── home.html
│   ├── page.html
│   └── post.html
├── LICENSE.txt
├── README.md
└── _sass
    ├── minima
    │   ├── _base.scss
    │   ├── _layout.scss
    │   └── _syntax-highlighting.scss
    └── minima.scss&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are folders of the minima template that contain all the files, scripts and templates required to put together your webpage. To override any of the defualt behavious, as is done in many of the add on tutorials linked to in this blog, we need to make the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_includes&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_layouts&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_sass&lt;/code&gt; folders available in our project directory by copy-pasting them there.&lt;br /&gt;
Hence forth, Jekyll would use the versions of these special name directories avaiable in our own project directory rather than the default theme &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Gemfile&lt;/code&gt; from which it was taking these files earlier. This allows us to make changes to the default &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;post.html&lt;/code&gt; template. Modifying the template opens the door to things like adding a line that computes the estimated &lt;a href=&quot;http://planetjekyll.github.io/snippets/reading-time&quot;&gt;read time&lt;/a&gt;, adding analytics and LaTeX typesetting support among other things. For more, see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/themes/#overriding-theme-defaults&quot;&gt;overriding&lt;/a&gt; tutorial from the Jekyll documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;monitoring-traffic-with-google-analytics&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring Traffic with Google Analytics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wish to see how many hits your blog is getting, you could choose to create a google analytics (GA) profile and add some code snippets as is explained in this well written blog post on &lt;a href=&quot;https://desiredpersona.com/google-analytics-jekyll/&quot;&gt;adding analytics to Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. The post assumes that the project has an &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_includes&lt;/code&gt; directory in case your project does not already have one by defualt, you could simply create an empty &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_includes&lt;/code&gt; directory and populate it with the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;analytics.html&lt;/code&gt; file as described in the tutorial. However, simply doing this might be insufficient since the tutorial also tells us to add a few lines of code to a certain &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;head.html&lt;/code&gt; file. The simplest way to cater to all these requirements is to populate the project directory with the complete folder structure as was described in the previous section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A caveat here is that the GA identification code for a website is publily accessible. This opens up the possibility of misuse through an deliberate or accidental attack that uses the same analytics code on another webpage. The good thing is that GA allows us to create filters to take care of such possiblities as has been described &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/49419250/is-sharing-google-analytics-tracking-id-safe&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The instructions are as follows,&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the google anayltics control view, in the lower left corner go to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;admin&lt;/code&gt; menu (The gear symbol)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;All Filters&lt;/code&gt; menu in the left most panel and click &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Add Filter&lt;/code&gt; to create a new &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;custom-filter&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create an &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;inclusive&lt;/code&gt; type filter and choose &lt;em&gt;Hostname&lt;/em&gt; as the Filter Field&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the hostname field enter the domain name of your website, for instance for this webpage I used &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ishank-juneja\.github\.io&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Save the filer and head back to the three pane admin interface, in the right most pane select the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Filters&lt;/code&gt; option, and apply the filter you created earlier to the GA code associated with the webpage you are protecting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This filter should exclude any spurious views arising from domain names other than your own&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;make-your-blog-interactive&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make your Blog Interactive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re like me, you would agree that an interactive element is still missing from the current setup. &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/&quot;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; is a free to use blog comment hosting service that comes pre-integrated with Jekyll. To add disqus comments to a blog simply, one may follow the instructions &lt;a href=&quot;https://desiredpersona.com/disqus-comments-jekyll/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; which happen to be by the same author that wrote the piece on adding analytics to a jekyll webpage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A problem with Disqus is that, it asks for an email address from a viewer before it lets them leave a comment. Personally I feel this might be too much to ask for. A way around, to let viwers interact more seamlessly with your blog would be to enable &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.disqus.com/en/articles/2199501-reactions&quot;&gt;disqus reactions&lt;/a&gt;. Be sure to enable this before pushing the code changes mentioned in the linked tutorial that make Disqus initiate. This is because the inclusion of reactions, does not apply retrospectively to blog posts (rather URLs) that existed prior to its enabling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;be-found-on-the-web&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be Found on the Web&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have gone through the trouble of creating your own webpage, you probably want your work to be found through Google (or other) search engines. This is where &lt;a href=&quot;https://search.google.com/search-console/about&quot;&gt;search console&lt;/a&gt; comes in. To help Google index your webpage more thoroughly, you can follow the instructions in &lt;a href=&quot;https://victor2code.github.io/blog/2019/07/04/jekyll-github-pages-appear-on-Google.html&quot;&gt;this tutorial&lt;/a&gt;. The indexing and subsequent visibility of your webpage as a top search result will take a few days to come into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;latex-for-the-web&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LaTeX for the Web&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;h4 id=&quot;with-mathjax&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;With MathJax&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical posts inevitably involve mathematical symbols, equations and relationships. The software &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latex-project.org/about/&quot;&gt;LaTeX&lt;/a&gt; is perhaps the most popular and efficient method of producing documents with typesetted mathematics. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mathjax.org/#gettingstarted&quot;&gt;MathJax&lt;/a&gt; is a type setting service for rendering mathematics typed using LaTeX on the web. It works by placing typeset mathematics at the appropriate location by first rendering the graphic object on their server and then delivering it to your website using a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cloudflare.com/en-in/learning/cdn/what-is-a-cdn/&quot;&gt;CDN&lt;/a&gt;. The setup required to make MathJax start working is quite minimal and is expalined in &lt;a href=&quot;http://sgeos.github.io/github/jekyll/2016/08/21/adding_mathjax_to_a_jekyll_github_pages_blog.html&quot;&gt;this blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; 
Once the setup is done, you can start to typeset inline and centered mathematics in a manner similar to the examples below,&lt;br /&gt;
Here we use inline math for the Pythagorean theorem: \( a^2 + b^2 = c^2\). This math in raw text looked like &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\\( a^2 + b^2 = c^2\\)&lt;/code&gt;. Next we have Euler’s famous result as display math, 
\[ e^{i \pi} + 1 = 0\]
Which could have been typset as &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\\[ e^{i \pi} + 1 = 0\\]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;h4 id=&quot;with-pandoc&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;With Pandoc&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case we wish to make an existing &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; file compatible with the web, we can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandoc.org/&quot;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt;. Pandoc can be installed using &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo apt-get install pandoc&lt;/code&gt;. Once installed, we can covert an existing LaTeX file, with a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; extension into a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.html&lt;/code&gt; file using the command&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pandoc -s name-of-the-file.tex --mathjax -o name-of-the-file.html&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
This is preferable if the contents of the document are to remain unchanged, however, if significant changes are to be made, it would be easier to make them to a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/code&gt; file rather than an &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;html&lt;/code&gt; file. Pandoc provides the option to convert a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; file to Markdown directly using the command&lt;br /&gt; &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pandoc -s name-of-the-file.tex --mathjax -o name-of-the-file.md&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;br /&gt; 
Though alright in principle, I found two practical difficulties with this approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Display math is not rendered correctly since &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Markdown + MathJax&lt;/code&gt; requires the use of formatting of the type&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-latex&quot; data-lang=&quot;latex&quot;&gt;Some text prior

&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\Big&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;_{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;i &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}^{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;i b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\Big&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\leq&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\Big&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;_{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;i &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}^{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\Big&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\Big&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;_{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;i &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}^{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\Big&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;$$&lt;/span&gt;

Some text after&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some text prior&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Big(\sum_{i = 1}^{n} a_i b_i\Big)^2 \leq 
\Big(\sum_{i = 1}^{n} a_i^2\Big) \Big(\sum_{i = 1}^{n} b_i^2\Big)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some text after&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;However the auto-generated output from pandoc would give something like the following instead&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-latex&quot; data-lang=&quot;latex&quot;&gt;Some text prior &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\Big&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;_{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;i &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}^{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;i b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\Big&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\leq&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\Big&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;_{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;i &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}^{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\Big&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\Big&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;_{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;i &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}^{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\Big&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;$$&lt;/span&gt; Some text after&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some text prior &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Big(\sum_{i = 1}^{n} a_i b_i\Big)^2 \leq 
\Big(\sum_{i = 1}^{n} a_i^2\Big) \Big(\sum_{i = 1}^{n} b_i^2\Big)&lt;/script&gt; Some text after&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Even with inline math, I observed that there were some problems with rendering some fonts, for instance &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$\mathcal{V}$&lt;/code&gt; was not producing correct results, moreover its presence was distorting subsequent text.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of these problems show up in the html version of these files. As I understand the reason for this is that the html file created by pandoc has explicit tags rather than $ symbols which makes all code unambiguous to MathJax. In my opinion, to get the best of both worlds, an easy workaround is to first create an html file using pandoc, then change its file extension to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; so that it can be edited like a Markdown file while having all the math correctly rendered using html tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MathJax is not as powerful as native TeX and there would likely be some other compatibility issues between the contents of a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; file and what MathJax is capable of. Some alternatives to MathJax to typeset math are &lt;a href=&quot;https://katex.org/&quot;&gt;KaTeX&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://latex.now.sh/&quot;&gt;LaTeX.css&lt;/a&gt;. These require some additional setup and I couldn’t get them to work on my webpage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;in-conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While getting my webpage up and running and subsequently adding snippets of copy-pasted html and JavaScript to implement the add ons, often times instructions were unclear. When stuck, or even when starting off, the best way to be done might be to either download or fork the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ishank-juneja/ishank-juneja.github.io&quot;&gt;source repository&lt;/a&gt; for this webpage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This post illustrates how to get a Jekyll static site up and running with some useful add-ons and tips. Rather than be a self contained post, this serves as more of a collection of pointers to other useful resources around the internet that when taken together get the job done. The tutorial and linked instructions assume a linux system with a bash shell available. Further familiarity with creating content for the Web with Markdown is assumed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Electronic Stethoscope Front-End</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/projects/course/steth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Electronic Stethoscope Front-End" /><published>2020-05-24T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-05-24T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/projects/course/steth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/projects/course/steth/">&lt;p&gt;A traditional Stethoscope acquires body signals acoustically. The sounds reach a doctor’s ears through
rubber tubes. The ability to make accurate inferences from these sounds is limited by the physicians
experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Goal of this project was to conceptualize an instrumentation circuit capable of filtering out and amplifying
Internal Body Sounds. Achieving this drastically reduces the dependence of diagnosis on the sensitivity
of a medical practitioner’s ear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end result was a microphone fed electronic circuit capable of displaying heart sounds on an oscilloscope.
A major aspect of the project was identifying and eliminating sources of noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Complete Schematic for Design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/schematic_steth.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stethoscope&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Result with characteristic peaks corresponding to the Lub-Dub sounds of Heart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/steth.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stethoscope&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A traditional Stethoscope acquires body signals acoustically. The sounds reach a doctor’s ears through rubber tubes. The ability to make accurate inferences from these sounds is limited by the physicians experience.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review of Man’s Search for Meaning, by Viktor Frankl</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/meaning" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review of Man’s Search for Meaning, by Viktor Frankl" /><published>2018-10-09T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-10-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/meaning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/meaning">&lt;p&gt;Staying intrinsically motivated is important for self-improvement and progress. I have always wanted to understand factors that influence motivation and I found Frankl’s book to be extremely insightful in this regard. There are numerous accounts of the Holocaust that go into detail about atrocities committed in the dreaded concentration camps of Nazi Germany. This book is unique in that it discusses Psychological aspects of imprisonment, torture, starvation and suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the very start Frankl paints a vivid picture of life in Auschwitz and other camps. He focuses on the everyday sufferings that made life seem like a burden to prisoners. A few things really stood out to me about life in concentration camps. People were robbed completely of their identities and their existence was reduced to a mere number. Inmates were forced to work long hours performing intensive manual labour, and at the same time their diets were limited to a few slices of bread and a single serving of soup. Life and death were extremely unpredictable and a prisoner could be executed on the whim of a guard. It is fascinating that under this kind of an atmosphere, inmates still managed to have light-hearted discussions and steal a few moments to appreciate art and partake in humour.
A major theme in the book that I found interesting, is the progression of an inmate’s mental state through three stages; Shock about the state of affairs at camp, entrenchment into the camp routine, and the reaction following their release. On arrival at a camp location, many inmates were directly sent to the gas chambers and crematoriums. The survivors of this event considered themselves lucky to be alive, but soon their gratitude turned into despair as they endured through camp life. The struggles included being stripped of all their clothes and possessions, walking barefoot over ice leading to frostbite and contracting infections due to their damaging lifestyles. 
Soon, starvation and constant physical pain reduced people in concentration camps to primitive beings. Their thoughts were limited to food and survival. Frankl describes the horrific way in which people dropped dead from disease, injuries and exhaustion during this time. Omnipresent death and suffering lead to a sense of apathy among the inmates. These traits marked the second stage of camp life. Reading about this caused me to think deeply about the ideas of humanity and morality – things that supposedly make us human. Values like these differentiate us from animals, however, in the absence of all the comforts of daily life we are not above the nourishment needs of our bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankl emphasises that humans are peculiar in that they can only be content in the present by looking to and hoping for a better future. In fact, the author goes a step further and says, even suffering can become bearable if we look at how the experience could be of value to us in future through a possible silver lining. To validate these ideas he points to anecdotal evidence from his time at the camp. Prisoners who lost faith in the future would become subject to mental decay, and sooner or later they would perish. For other prisoners, the motivation to survive came from looking forward to life after their eventual homecoming. 
On understanding Frankl’s thoughts on motivation, I looked back to my own life and all the achievements that I was proud of. I have found myself in complete agreement with the view that the key to a meaningful life is to rise up to challenges that are sent our way. However, despite all the struggle, it is possible that we do not reach the goal we strived for. This is not something to lament over, since our struggles have intrinsic value of their own. Instead we should accept our situation and persevere towards our goal.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This review was written for a course assignment for the Introduction to Psychology course at IIT Bombay&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Staying intrinsically motivated is important for self-improvement and progress. I have always wanted to understand factors that influence motivation and I found Frankl’s book to be extremely insightful in this regard. There are numerous accounts of the Holocaust that go into detail about atrocities committed in the dreaded concentration camps of Nazi Germany. This book is unique in that it discusses Psychological aspects of imprisonment, torture, starvation and suffering.</summary></entry></feed>